[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is some questions on the shorter note on anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it, eh... in the second paragraph, gives us, yeah, sutta quotes, just giving the basic, eh... characteristics of a determined thing, which are, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll read the English translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Disappearance is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Change while standing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems, at first glance, one would think the order would be different, that it would be arising, then changing while standing, and then ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a reason why it's given in this order?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because that order is rooted in a completely mistaken, wrong view of the external point of view, in regard to the experience, in regard to the fundamentals of space and time.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, people assume the external world, which is independent of me and my experience, and that external world is also, sort of, possesses time in which we are placed, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, time kind of stands for that external assumption of yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you think that you have a reason, you're enduring, and then you're ceasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that requires an external reference point to see that kind of flow,
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is actually impossible to see internally, because you can't step outside of yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can have that notion of a flow, of a flux, in regard to external things around you, in regard to objects of your senses, but you cannot have that kind of, eh... reference point in regard to your own senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the... that's why, eh... it can only be described and seen internally, phenomenologically, which is how the Buddha described it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arising is manifest, or disappearing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or,
[SPEAKER_02]: Changing while standing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you look at the nature of arising, it's like fading in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means there is no first point before which thing wasn't and then it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you caught the moment where it appeared.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: That can only be done in an external manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you're trying to apply to your own
[SPEAKER_02]: situation and the senses, the sense bases, you cannot see it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you look at it, you see that either are already, sorry, they're either already fading in or either fading out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter which.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is persisting while changing, or changing while standing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you have something fading in, means it's increasing in its presence, means it's staying the same thing while it's increasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's just another way of saying it's changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: If something is fading out, as in it's de-intensifying in its presence, again, it stays the same thing, you can still designate it as the same thing, while it's changing, as in it's fading out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether it's arising or changing, you can say it's persisting while... well, sorry, whether it's arising or disappearing, you can say that it's persisting while changing, just in a different direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the Buddha would describe arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, persisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are three ways of looking at an arisen present phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either intensifying, de-intensifying, which is either way to see it as changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's often heard in meditation instructions is this idea of, you know, things are constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard all kinds of ideas, like every fraction of a second, measuring it in nanoseconds, femtoseconds, these little moments of being and such things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the idea, I guess, of watching changes to prove something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's quite unfortunate that that sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, unfortunate but not surprising that that's how we... because it is the external point of view of ourselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like one of the fundamental wrong views that can be manifested... that can manifest itself in different ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: But presently, contemporarily, the most common way is the scientific outlook, as in you see yourself inhabiting this public world, that it's there before you and it's going to carry on after you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But any notions of the world that you can have, it's based on your experience as a whole, on your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you having a view that it's independent of that because of which that view is there in the first place, that's why it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as I... as I said just... just a few seconds ago, any notion of flux requires a... a non-changing reference point.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can see things are flowing against this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can do that in regard to your sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you cannot do that in regard to your sense bases and sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, you cannot step outside of the five aggregates and your situation as a whole and then see it as it's constantly changing or even measure the nanofractions of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can come up with a pleasing theory and a very neat description of it, but that would require a person to inhabit that wrong view of the external world in regard to myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then everything will make sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because it's rooted in that misperception of the fundamental aspects of your situation, it cannot result in any knowledge, in any wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: He writes, shortly after, that these three characteristics of the determined, or characteristics whereby what is determined may be known as such, precisely indicate the fundamental structure in virtue of which things are things, in virtue of which, that is to say, things are distinct one from another.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is also virtue of this structure that all experience, including the arahants, is intentional or teleological, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: that things are significant.
[SPEAKER_01]: They point to other possible things.
Eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not exactly clear what is meant when he's saying... Obviously, we can say this thing is the same thing, because we can see that it's enduring at some level.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the idea that also these three characteristics are that by... that kind of... that by which there are intentions and significances to things at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how do we say that
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing a thing enduring or fading in, fading out, refers to intentionality in any way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's based on it, because changing while remaining the same requires, well, it requires at least two different levels of that generality.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires a certain sameness, while within that, so simultaneously present to that sameness, that thing is changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Until the
[SPEAKER_02]: Has changed to such a degree that then, abruptly, you just see now it's a different thing present there, as in your experience has changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that in itself, it's already intentional.
[SPEAKER_02]: The things on the lower level of generality, that's why he talks about the fundamental structure, are bound by that general determination of still being the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: When that changes to a greater degree, and that determination ceases.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the basis of any intentionality.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the basis of any choices you can make.
[SPEAKER_02]: The possibilities that are implied in the given experience as a whole, are within that experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in return, they actually determine that experience as a whole, for what you know it, how you know it.